A Guide to Porgy and Bess: A Contemporary Collection of Posters from the 1950s
Copyright George Mason University Libraries
Special Collections and Archives, George Mason University Libraries
Porgy and Bess: A Collection of Posters from the 1950s
Special Collections and Archives, George Mason University
Porgy and Bess 001
60 posters
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Biographical/Historical Information
Porgy and Bess was a three act "folk Opera" produced by The Theatre Guild at the Alvin Theatre, New York City, in 1927. The Opera was taken directly from a book by Dubose Heyward titled Porgy, with lyrics and music by Ira and George Gershwin. The opera revolves around Porgy, a physically-challenged African-American black beggar who lives and works in a Charleston tenement called Catfish Row and who loves the beautiful but weak-willed Bess. Bess is the mistress of the vicious Crown, but when Crown flees after murdering a man, she goes to live with Porgy. On Crown's return porgy fights with him and kills him. Porgy is taken to jail, and while there Bess is lured away by the drug peddler, Sportin' Life. When Porgy gets out of jail, he leaves Catfish Row to find Bess. This is where the play ends. The play remains one of the greatest of all American folk dramas.
Robert Breen was the first Person to arrange postwar United States and Soviet cultural "changes. He also helped to bring federal financing to the performing arts. His greatest success was on the international stage in 1952. He directed and co-produced with Blevins Davis the critically acclaimed revival of Porgy and Bess. It toured twenty-nine countries in four years. The following is a brief account of the opera's successful tours through North and South America and Europe.
The United States performances began in Chicago and had a slow start because of the summer heat and the preoccupation with the Republican National Convention. But, before long the tour became a huge success. Critics called the performances of Porgy and Bess, "the best sung version yet,"' and by the end of their stay in Chicago the cast was performing to standing room only crowds.
From Chicago, the troupe traveled to Vienna, Austria for the opening of their European tour on September 7, 1952. In the past, Vienna had never been very receptive to American opera, but after Porgy and Bess, attitudes changed dramatically. The crowds went wild: they had never seen anything like it before in a theater. The next stop was Berlin and there, too, the audiences loved Porgy and Bess. It became the main event for a month-long festival. The reactions of the audiences were extraordinary, even though many could not understand what was being spoken or sung.
Europeans were not the only ones to notice the amazing success of Porgy and Bess. In the United States people were also taking notice of Porgy and Bess, including President Dwight Eisenhower. He created an emergency fund with an annual appropriation of five million dollars. This fund was used to finance and promote "American" cultural activities, such as Porgy and Bess. Half the money went to theater productions. The economics of production demanded full houses, so when there was a period of empty seats in Europe, Billy Rose proposed bringing the tour home to the United States. But before going home, they traveled to Paris for one last performance. The reactions were the same as in Vienna and Berlin. Gendarmes were needed to keep those without tickets from crashing the gates. Critics called Porgy and Bess, "A masterpiece ... one doesn't have to say more. ,2 After Paris, the troupe returned to perform at the Ziegfeld Theatre in New York City. While there, the cast performed 305 shows and while still in New York, the popularity of Porgy and Bess picked up in Europe. The troupe was invited to revisit Paris, intending to stay only three weeks, but demand kept the opera performing for an additional seven weeks. From Paris, the opera moved to Zagreb, Yugoslavia. This was the first time American singers were invited behind the Iron Curtain.
Their next stop was Egypt, first Alexandria and then Cairo. The first performance in Alexandria was on New Year's Eve, and critics were skeptical about the shows success, but the cast played to a packed house, while hundreds more were turned away. From Alexandria, they traveled to Cairo, where, once again, they were a huge success. Next, the troupe traveled to Tel Aviv, Israel, where they performed eight shows at the Habimah Theatre. People literally tackled the ticket takers so that they could get inside the theater.
From Israel, the opera traveled to Barcelona, Spain. Here, they performed for ten days, and critics called Porgy and Bess "the best thing seen in Barcelona in twenty years."' From there they traveled to Italy, first to Milan and the world-renowned Teatro Alla Scala. For many in the cast it was a lifelong dream to perform in the Teatro Alla Scala. They did not let anyone down -- they performed as never before. It was the first time an American company had been invited to one of the world's premier opera houses. After Milan, the cast performed in Genoa and Florence, Lausanne, Marseilles, and back to Italy to perform in Turin and Rome. After Italy, they traveled to Zurich, and finished this leg of the European tour in Brussels and Antwerp.
The troupe then changed direction, traveling south to Rio de Janeiro, and Lima. The audiences in South America thought Porgy and Bess was a revelation, and worthy of unrestricted applause.
From South America, they went to the Soviet Union, first Leningrad and then Moscow. There were some misunderstandings on opening night in Leningrad because audiences had trouble understanding things such as the buzzard over Porgy's abode and the open attitudes about sexual passion. The Russians appeared to suffer from culture shock. By the end of the Leningrad tour, however, the cast was once again a huge success and played to full houses and enthusiastic audiences. Next, they appeared in Moscow where the cast felt more comfortable because the theater audiences were more accepting than the ones in Leningrad. On the second night the cast was honored by the attendance of the three most important Soviet politicians: Nikita Khrushchev, Nikolai Bulganin, and Vyacheslav Molotov. This was a rare occurrence because the leaders rarely attended public performances: when they did, it had always been on the last night.
The next stops were again behind the Iron Curtain, Warsaw, and Prague. The performances were a huge success and once again tickets sold out before the performances began. After the troupe left Warsaw and Prague, they traveled to Germany, where they performed in Munich, Stuttgart, Dtisseldorf, and Hamburg. From Germany they traveled to Rotterdam, Netherlands, Aachus, Denmark and back to the Netherlands, this time in Amsterdam, where the tour ended on June 3, 1956.
Arrangement
Posters are arranged alphabetically according to the country where the performances were held.
Contents List
- Porgy and Bess Posters
  - Antwerp, Belgium: Hippodrome Theatre, June 23-30, 1955; 22"x14"; Vertical; black background with yellow lettering; white squares with black lettering; white border
  - Antwerp, Belgium: Hippodrome Theater, June 23-30,1955; 34"x24"; Large black background with bright yellow lettering; white squares with black lettering; white border
  - Antwerp, Belgium: Hippodrome Theater, June 23-30,1955; 31"x96"; Black background with white squares and black lettering; large bright yellow lettering in the middle of "Porgy and Bess".
  - Brussels, Belgium: Theatre de la Monnaie, June 23-30,1955; 32"x24"; Black background with white squares and black lettering; off white border; large lemon yellow letters in middle; yellow square at top with black lettering
  - Rio de Janeiro, Brazil: Brazil Teatro Municipal, July 7-13,1955; 60"x92"; Four pieces; bright red background with off white border and white lettering inside of it
  - Prague, Czechoslovakia: Kerlin Theatre, February 11-19,1956; 34"x24"; Washed out off-white background; small black lettering, larger bold red lettering; on the left side there is a square with the words "Porgy and Bess".
  - Prague, Czechoslovakia: Kerlin Theatre, February 11-19,1956; 42"x31"; Salmon colored fibrous paper with black charted lettering
  - Arhus, Denmark: Aarhushallen, May 9-16,1956; 33"x25"; White background in middle with lime-green lettering and black writing;black and white photographs taken from characters and scenes of the play act as the boder.
  - Alexandria, Egypt: Theatre Mohamad Aly December 31,1954-January 2, 1955, 69"x36"; White background; blue border with white starts; blue and red lettering
  - Alexandria, Egypt: Theatre Mohamad Aly December 31,1954-January 2, 1955, 12"x8"; Small washed out cream-color background; black border with red and black lettering; two star illustrations on either side
  - Cairo, Egypt: Theatre De'L Opera January 7-12,1955, 11"x8"; Washed out brown background; red and black lettering; four different versions
  - Cairo, Egypt: Theatre De'L Opera January 7-12, 1955, 69"x36"; White background; blue star border; blue and red lettering; Egyptian lettering at top.
  - Marseilles, France: Opera Municpal March 26-April 4,1955, 18"x12"; Off-white background;red and blue lettering
  - Marseilles, France: Opera Municpal March 26-April 4,1955, 55"x36"; Large; bright purple with black lettering.
  - Paris, France: Theatre De'L Empire February 16-March 1,1953, 24"x16"; Green backround with black and white lettering
  - Paris, France: Theatre De'L Empire September 30-December 4,1954, 64"x94",48"x34"; Large;green background with large black lettering
  - Paris, France: Theatre De'L Empire September 30-December 4,1954, 24"x16"; Vertical;dark green background with white border;large bold black lettering
  - Paris, France: Theatre De'L Empire September 30-December 4,1954, 59"x40",59"x37"; Green background; large black lettering
  - Berlin,Germany: Titania Palast September 18-27,1952, 23"x33"; Off-white background with blue sketch-like illustration of village; magenta and black lettering through the center
  - Dusseldorf,Germany: Apolla Theatre November 18-22,1955, 24"x34"; Lemon yellow background with orenge border on the top and bottom; orange and black lettering
  - Dusseldorf,Germany: Apolla Theatre November 18-22,1955, 24"x34"; White background with black lettering; blue patch with Porgy and Bess written in yellow in the middle
  - Frankfort,Germany: Stadtischen Buhnen November 25-27,1955, 24"x33"; White background with black lettering; blue patch of color in middle with "Porgy and Bess" written in bright yellow
  - Franfort,Germany: Stadtischen Buhnen November 25-27,1955, 24"x34"; Lemon yellow background; black border on sides; orange border on top and bottom; black and orange lettering
  - Hamburg,Germany: Opera House March 7-11,1956, 23"x33"; Brick colored border surrounding off-white background; brick colored lettering
  - Munich,Germany: Deutsches Theatre December 1-6,1955, 48"x33"; Black and white background with large yellow, black, and white lettering
  - Munich,Germany: Deutsches Theatre February 22-29,1956, 48"x33"; Two pieces; bright red background with bright yellow lettering reading "Porgy and Bess" across the front
  - Stuttgart,Germany: Staats Theatre March 1-4,1956, 51"x34"; Two pieces; black background with large yellow lettering in the middle
  - Tel Aviv,Israel: Habimah Theatre January 26-30,1955, 37"x25"; White background with blue border; red and blue lettering; bigger letters in the middle than in the rest of poster
  - Florence,Italy: Teatro Comunale March 9-13,1955, 27"x13"; Vertical; off-white background with red and black lettering
  - Florence, Italy: Teatro Comunale March 9-13,1955, 48"x33";Mustart-yellow background with black lettering;red lettering in upper half; Two purple stamp-like pictures on lower left part; tear running through title. ("Porgy and Bess")
  - Genoa, Italy: Teatro Carlo Felice March 1-6,1955, 40"x14"; Vertical; beige background with brown and red lettering;has a shield-like emblem border at the top
  - Milan, Italy: Teatro Alla Scala February 23-27,1955, 28"x40"; Bright yellow background; lists names in black lettering with red lettering in the upper half.
  - Milan, Italy: Teatro Allo Scala February 23-27,1955, 15"x11",40"x28",80"x40"; Light brown background with dark brown lettering; red cross on shield at top; decorative leafy-style border
  - Naples, Italy: Teatro Di San Carlo February 15-17,1955, 39"x28"; Bright blue background with a yellow and green illustration of village; white border; white lettering.
  - Naples, Italy: Teatro Di San Carlo February 15-17,1955, 52"x38, 37"x26"; Bright yellow background; balck lettering; red lettering at top; very simple.
  - Naples, Italy: Teatro Di San Carlo February 15-17,1955, 22"x13"; Bright mustard yellow background; brown border; red and brown lettering.
  - Rome, Italy: Teatro Quattro Fontane April 21-May 14,1955, 10"x7"; Small white playbills with red and blue lettering; writing on front and back.
  - Rome, Italy: Teatro Quattro Fontane April 21-May 14,1955, 55"x40",78"x54"; Bright mustard-yellow background with black and red lettering
  - Rome, Italy: Teatro Quattro Fontane April 21-May 14,1955, 40"x14"; Vertical; blue background with black and red lettering
  - Rome, Italy: Teatro Quattro Fontane April 21-May 14,1955, 40"x14"; Vertical; yellow background with black and red lettering
  - Rome, Italy: Teatro Quattro Fontane April 21-May 14,1955, 80"x54"; Three pieces; green and bright yellow background fading into one another; large red lettering at top; black lettering at bottom; very bright and colorful
  - Turin, Italy: Teatro Alfieri April 9-17,1955, 27"x13"; Vertical; off-white pink illustration of a lady in the background; large red lettering towards top
  - Turin, Italy: Teatro Alfieri April 9-17,1955, 38"x26"; Pink and yellow illustration with black lettering
  - Venice, Italy: Teatro La Fenice September 22-25, 1954, 40"x28"; Vibrant red background with half facial photo of Gershwin in upper right, illustration of Porgy and Bess on left; black and whitw lettering.
  - Venice, Italy: Teatro La Fenice September 22-25, 1954, 40"x14"; A number of these in the background colors of: yellow, blue-green, blue, washed-out, white, and pink; black and red lettering;vertical
  - Venice, Italy: Teatro La Fenice September 22-25, 1954, 55"x39"; Large; off-white; red and black lettering.
  - Amsterdam, Netherlands: Teatre Carre May 19-June3, 1956, 49"x33"; White border; black lettering within white squares; yellow squares with black lettering; bright yellow lettering in very middle
  - Lima, Peru: Teatro Municipal September 3-7, 1955, 52"x34"; Two pieces; washed-out white background with black lettering
  - Warsaw, Poland: National Opera House January 24-February 1, 1954, 40"x28";White background; blue and red lettering.
  - Barcelona, Spain: Gran Teatro Del Liceo February 3-13, 1955, 50"x35"; Large; off-white with brown and red lettering; branch style border with leaves on it.
  - Lausanne, Switzerland: Theatre De Beaulieu March 16-23, 1955, 28"x14", 50"x36"; Washed-out yellow background with black and red lettering; bold red lettering in the middle.
  - Lausanne, Switzerland: Teatre De Beaulieu March 16-23, 1955, 11"x8";Washed-out white with red and black lettering; bold red lettering in the middle.
  - Zurich, Switzerland: Hallenstadion June 3-12, 1955, 50"x36";Light green background with painted color figures of Porgy and Bess; black sketch of village behind them; blue lettering at top; black lettering throughhout the rest.
  - Zurich, Switzerland: Hallenstadion June 3-12, 1955, 20"x12"; Black border with lettering surrounding light green background; painted color figures of Porgy and Bess; black line sketch of village behind them; blue lettering at top.
  - Chicago, USA: Ciciv Opera House June 25, 1952, 20"x14"; Two shades of orange background; black and white lettering; illustration of Porgy and Bess dancing in the middle
  - New York, USA: Ziegfeld Theatre March 10-November 28,1953, 9"x6"; Small; off-white flyer with black border; stars on sides; black writing; illustration of village in black.
  - Leningrad, USSR: Palace of Culture December 26-January 5,1956, 42"x28"; White background; blue and red lettering in upper half.
  - Moscow, USSR: Stanilavsky Theatre January 10-17, 1956, 40"x27"; White background; blue and red lettering; blue lettering in bottom half
  - Zagreb, Yugoslavia: Theatre De'L Opera December 11-14, 1954, 39"x28"; White background; purple and white lettering
  - Zagreb, Yugoslavia: Theatre De'L Opera Dec 11-14, 1954, 12"x8"; White background; red and black lettering; writing on both sides.